Papers of James Keith, President, Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals, 1843-1910 (bulk 1877-1910)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Papers of James Keith, President, Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals, 1843-1910 (bulk 1877-1910)
The Library of Virginia
31211
1 cu. ft. (3 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred by Allen L. Lucy, Clerk, Supreme Court of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia. 26 September 1981.
Biographical/Historical Information
James Keith was born 7 September 1839 in Fauquier County, Virginia. He studied law at the University of Virginia, as well as under John M. Forbes of Warrenton. Keith also served the Confederate States during the Civil War as part of the Black Horse Calvary. He was elected to the Virginia House of Delegates in 1869, serving one session before being elected to the Eleventh Judicial Circuit in 1870. This court oversaw cases from Alexandria, Fauquier and surrounding counties. Keith served as a circuit court judge until 1895 when he was elected to the Supreme Court of Appeals in Richmond, later serving as the court's President (now known as Chief Justice). Judge Keith retired from the Supreme Court of Appeals in 1916 and died in 1918.
Scope and Content
Contains a variety of items and documents belonging to Judge James Keith, President of the Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals. The material includes lists of appeals granted and refused, incoming and outgoing correspondence related to personal and court matters, court papers, and speeches. The correspondence includes letters to United States Secretary of War and Secretary of State, Elihu Root, fellow Supreme Court judges John Buchanan and John Harlan, as well as a folder of letters detailing events surrounding the election of 1896. Also included is a speech given by Judge Keith about General Eppa Hunton, and two sets of remarks regarding the installation of portraits in the court house. Additionally, the collection includes a set of Virginia Bar Examination questions from 1900, titled "Questions Propounded by the Court of Appeals to Applicants for License to Practice Law." The original order of the material was maintained as much as possible.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Appeals Granted and Refused, 1877-1910
Series II. Correspondence, 1894-1910
Series III. Miscellaneous Papers, 1843-1910
Contents List
- Series I. Appeals Granted and Refused, 1877-1910.
  Contains five notebooks of appeals granted and refused. The notebooks contain lists of cases with varying amounts of information, such as the date, case number, names of platintiffs and defendents, whether the appeal was granted, which judge oversaw the case, and which session it was part of (Richmond, Staunton, Winchester, or Wytheville). The notebooks with overlapping dates contain different information.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Appeals granted and refused (cases heard after Judge Moncure retired), 1877-1879. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Appeals granted and refused, 1895-1896. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Appeals granted and refused, 1896-1902. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Appeals granted and refused, 1896-1902. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Appeals granted and refused, 1903-1910. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II. Correspondence, 1894-1910.
  Contains letters to and from Chief Justice James Keith. The content of the letters includes genealogical and family-related subjects, as well as discussion of court decisions, his Civil War service, and the 1896 presidential election. Also included are letters to Presidents William McKinley and Theodore Roosevelt, as well as letters to Elihu Root who served as Secretary of War under McKinley and Secretary of State under Roosevelt. Some folders contain only letters to Justice Keith, others contain letters going both ways, and still others contain only copies of letters sent by Justice Keith.
  Arranged in two sections: correspondents with multiple letters (each correspondent gets a separate folder) and correspondents with single letters (many correspondents in one folder). Each section is arranged alphabetically by last name. At the end of the list is one subject folder (1896 election) and two folders of unidentified letters. The original order of the letters varied, and as such, this arrangement was the best compromise.
  - Multiple Letters.
    - Anderson, Archer, 1903. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Browning, Judith 1897. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Buchanan, Judge John A., 1905. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Burks, E.C. (Virginia Law Register), 1896. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Caskie and Coleman, 1905. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Cauthorn [?], Sara, 1897. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Davis, Richard, 1905. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Garden, Hugh, 1896-1904. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Harlan, Judge John, 1898-1905. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Grant, J.R., 1902-1903. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Keith, Annie, 1897-1899. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Keith, Mary, 1897. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Lane, William A., 1897. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lewis, William Draper, 1905. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Meigs, S.E., 1905. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Root, Elihu, 1901-1905. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Smith, Thomas, 1902-1906. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Tucker, J.R., 1896. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Young, S.B., 1897. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Single Letters.
    - Abbie and Imbrie - Braxton, 1894-1910. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Brewer - Hunton, 1899-1905. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Kate" - Logan, 1894-1900. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - McClanahan - Minor, 1898-1905. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Moore - Munford, 1894-1906. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Payne - Roosevelt, 1896-1903. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Stribling - West Publishing Company, 1905-1906. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous.
    - 1896 Presidential Campaign, 1895-1896. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Unidentified "Judge" letters, 1902. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Unidentified missing page, undated. (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Series III. Miscellaneous Papers, 1843-1910.
  Contains a variety of items including, but not limited to, financial documents, court papers, and speeches. Several of the documents are undated.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of document.
  - Checks, 1904. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Checks, 1905. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Checks, 1906. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Checks (stub book), 1910. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Court Documents (Green v. Smith), 1843-1879. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Court Opinion (W.O. Nolting v. National Bank of Virginia), undated. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Manual of the House of Delegates and Senate of Virginia, 1895-1896 Session, 1895. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Picture of Rufus W. Peckham (possibly a magazine insert), undated. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Questions Propounded by the Court of Appeals to Applicants for License to Practice Law, 1900. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Receipts, 1898-1905. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Speech (about General Eppa Hunton), undated. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Speech (portrait installation, "Mr. Taylor"), undated. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Speech (portrait installation, Judge Henry W. Thomas), undated. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Unidentified writings (possibly related to election), undated. (Box 3, Folder 11)